Women: Position and Progress Collection, 1804-2001
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Women: position and progress collection
1804-2001
MS 431
4 boxes, 30 volumes (3 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection contains manuscripts and published material, including books dating from the early nineteenth century. The collection consists primarily of published sources such as lectures, sermons, and printed material; but also includes a significant amount of unusual and unique material such as household bills and inventories, letters, lists, and notes.
The Women: Position and Progress Collection contains manuscript and published material, including books dating from the early nineteenth century. It documents both dominant attitudes about middle- and upper-class women's roles and gender-conscious women's and men's efforts to expand and overturn those roles, and illustrates the impact of such efforts on women's status and position in Western societies. The collection consists primarily of published sources such as articles, printed lectures and sermons, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets; but also includes a significant amount of unusual and unique material such as household bills and inventories, letters, lists, and notes.
About half the material in the collection dates from the nineteenth century. The bulk of material consists of articles, books, and pamphlets that reflect the widely divergent views about women's roles that made "the woman question" such a visible and contentious issue in this period. Prescriptive literature, such as advice books with titles such as How the Good Wife Taught Her Daughter, and The Young Bride's Book, and an assortment of printed lectures and sermons clearly illustrate the power and prevalence of traditional assumptions about women's "natural" maternalism and domesticity. Emerging arguments about the need for women's equality and women's rights are also well-represented in the older segment of the collection by articles from magazines and newspapers, pamphlets, and printed lectures. A few examples of personal letters, household bills, and lists of house rules for servants from a Worcester, Massachusetts home provide a small glimpse into the realities of daily life for upper- middle- and working-class women during the 1830s-80s.
The twentieth century material reflects a similar range of opinions about women's social, political, and economic roles, and documents the dramatic shifts in women's status over the last hundred years. Anti-feminist attitudes are primarily represented in a variety of articles and essays from both scholarly and popular publications. Feminist points of view as expressed in magazine and newspaper articles, scholarly essays, and speeches are far more evident in twentieth century material. Unusual items from the twentieth century includes a typewritten outline of the history of the women's movement in the U.S. compiled in 1944 by Mary Williams, a professor at Goucher College; a few personal letters; and a toy catalog which probably dates from the 1940s or 1950s.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this "artificial" subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. Some items may have been removed from other collections.
Search Terms
Etiquette for women--History--Sources; Housewives--History--Sources; Manners and customs--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Marriage--History--Sources; Middle class women--Attitudes; Motherhood--History--Sources; Women--Conduct of life; Women--Periodicals; Women's rights--History--20th century--Sources; Women's rights--History--19th century--Sources; Women--Sexual behavior--History; Women--Social and moral questions; Sophia Smith Collection
- Clippings 1889-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Exposition\ exhibitions 1876-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- History of women--general 1910-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Magazine articles, 19th century (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Magazine articles, 20th century (Box 1, Folder 5a-c)
- Pamphlets
  - 1804-98 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1900-40 (Box 2, Folder 7 a-c)
  - 1941-43, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Postcards undated (late 19th, early 20th century) (Box 3, Folder 8a)
- Manners and customs
  - American Woman's Home by Catharine Beecher and Harriet Beecher Stowe 1870 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Green, Mary: household bills 1833-35 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Green Hill, Worcester, MA: household lists 1874-88; rules for young school girlsundated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - May, Samuel J.: three letters to wife Lucretia 1835 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General and miscellaneous 1848-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pamphlets and booklets 1845-1959, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14-14a)
- Books
  - Lectures on Female Education and Manners by J. Burton. Baltimore 1811 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Noble Deeds of Woman; or, Examples of Female Courage and Virtue by Elizabeth Starling.1850 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Woman, in her Social and Domestic Character 1833, and New every morning, a year book for girls 1886 by Mrs. John Sandford (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Ladies Album 1856 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Maternal instruction by Elizabeth Helme 1804 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - How the goode wif thaught hir daughter, extracted from Hindley, Chas., ed. The Old Book Collector's Miscellany, v.2 1872 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Books on Shelf
  - Bracken, Peg. I Try to Behave Myself: Peg Bracken's Etiquette Book 1966
  - Bragdon, Elizabeth, editor. Women Today: Their Conflicts, Their Frustrations and Their Fulfillments 1953
  - Cole, Wolliam and Florett Robinson. Women are wonderful! A history in cartoons of a hundred years 1956
  - Copley, Esther. Female excellence, or hints to daughters designed for their use from the time of leaving school till their settlement in life circa 1850s
  - The Cosmopolitan Report: The Changing Life of American Women 1986
  - Dahl, Arlene. Always Ask a Man: Arlene Dahl's Key to Femininity 1965
  - Donnelly, Eleanor C., editor. Girlhood's Handbook of Woman: A Compendium of Views 1898
  - Dye, Judith Levett. For the instruction and amusement of Women: the growth, development, and definition of American magazines for women 1780-1840. University of Pennsylvania, Ph.D. 1977
  - Farmer, Lydia Hoyt, editor. The National Exposition Souvenir: What America Owes to Women 1893
  - Gilman, Charlotte Perkins. The Manmade World or Our Andocentric Culture 1911
  - The Good Housekeeping Woman's Almanac: The Book With All the Answers for Women by the editors of World Almanac 1977
  - The habits of good society: a handbook for ladies and gentlemen 1860
  - Hankins, Mary Louise. Women of New York 1861
  - Hersey, Heloise. To Girls: A budget of letters 1901
  - Holtby, Winifred. Women and a Changing Civilization 1935
  - Hosmer, William. The Young Lady's Book 1852
  - Life Magazine: The American Woman (special issue) Dec 24 1956
  - Martineau, Harriet. Household Education 1867
  - Massachusetts Review. Woman: An Issue 1972
  - Melendy, Mary. The Ideal Woman for Maidens, Wives, and Mothers 1911
  - Michelet, M.J. Woman (translated from the French by J.W. Palmer)1860
  - Rogers, Agnes. Women are here to stay 1949
  - Royden, Maude. Women's Partnership in the New World 1941
  - "This Crisis in History": Report of the Third Annual New York Herald Tribune Women's Conference on Current Problems, 1933
  - Thornwell, Emily. The ladies guide to perfect gentility 1856
  - Tobias, Roscoe Burdette and Mary E. Marcy. Women as Sex Vendors: or, why women are conservative, being a view of the economic status of women circa 1918
  - Vann. The Five Talents of Woman: A Book for Girls and Women 1895
  - West, Jane. Letters to a Young Lady in Which the Duties and Character of Women are Considered 1806
  - Wilcox, Ella Wheeler. Men, Women and Emotions 1893
  - Women: Pro and Con, a compilation of quotes about women, illustrated by Jeff Hill (Peter Pauper Press) 1958
  - Women's Partnership in the New World, by Maude Royden 1941
- "I'll be no submissive wife: a ballad" (sheet music), composed by Alex Lee 1838 (Map-case Flat File)